<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year><year>2026</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at

          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Introduction</title>
    <prepared>Péter Dimitrov</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2018-03-22</date>
    <rev>A</rev>
    <file>introduction.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>Purpose</title>
    <p>The Trivial File Transfer Protocol or TFTP is a very simple protocol
    used to transfer files.</p>
    <p>It has been implemented on top of the User Datagram protocol (UDP) so
    it may be used to move files between machines on different networks
    implementing UDP. It is designed to be small and easy to implement.
    Therefore, it lacks most of the features of a regular FTP.  The only
    thing it can do is read and write files (or mail) from/to a remote server.
    It cannot list directories, and currently has no provisions for user
    authentication.</p>
    <p>The <c>tftp</c> application implements the following IETF standards:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <url href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc1350">
          RFC 1350</url>, The TFTP Protocol (revision 2)
      </item>
      <item>
        <url href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc2347">
          RFC 2347</url>, TFTP Option Extension
      </item>
      <item>
        <url href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc2348">
          RFC 2348</url>, TFTP Blocksize Option</item>
      <item>
        <url href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc2349">
          RFC 2349</url>, TFTP Timeout Interval and Transfer Size Options
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>The only feature that not is implemented is the <c>netascii</c> transfer mode.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <p>It is assumed that the reader is familiar with the Erlang
      programming language, concepts of OTP, and has a basic
      understanding of the TFTP protocol.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security Considerations</title>
    <p>
      As stated in
      (<url href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc1350">RFC 1350</url>)
      be aware that "Since TFTP includes no login or access control mechanisms,
      care must be taken in the rights granted to a TFTP server process so as
      not to violate the security of the server hosts file system.
      TFTP is often installed with controls such that only files that have
      public read access are available via TFTP and writing files via TFTP
      is disallowed."
    </p>
    <p>
      This essentially means that any machine on the network
      that can reach the TFTP server is able to read and write,
      without authentication, any file on the machine that runs
      the TFTP server, that the user (or group) that runs the TFTP server
      (in this case the Erlang VM) is allowed to read or write.
      The machine configuration has to be prepared for that.
    </p>
    <warning>
      <p>
        The default behavior mentioned above is in general very risky,
        and as a remedy, this TFTP application's default callback
        <c>tftp_file</c> implements an initial state option
        <c>{root_dir,Dir}</c> that restricts the callback's file accesses
        to <c>Dir</c> and subdirectories.  It is recommended
        to use that option when starting start this TFTP server.
      </p>
    </warning>
  </section>
</chapter>
